you know Daniel what I was listening to
you I felt it was the self-portrait of a
future human because you were going on
all the elements and all the intricacies
that a future human that you would
actually see and know and care about it
for a whole system shift and if we take
them step by step as you said people
will listen to them and really examine
them you have the agenda for the future
human but here so I was you know knowing
you so well and feeling like you're an
evolutionary son
I felt I feel so proud to see an
illusionary son carrying with such grace
the full responsibility responsibility
able to respond to a radically new
situation with grace charm and actually
pleasure at how complex it is and I
think just that whole attitude is a very
great teaching for all of us when we
look at situations say I think it's too
much for me I would just look at you and
say no it's not you're here because it
isn't too much for you so thank you for
that I really felt that very deeply
often as you're sharing that Einstein's
comments we tend to esteem the esteem of
those whom we esteem comes to my mind
because means a lot to me to hear your
respect your comment in that way and
then you know the transpersonal
perspective how many of the same or
similar kinds of insights as we're in
these conversations each of us has come
to from very different backgrounds and
the places of commonality and overlap
but also the places of uniqueness and
difference is such a beautiful fun thing
and there really is like like I had
mentioned when you were talking there's
like a transmission of your being that
comes through what you teach and how you
teach it and you're and you're doing
that clearly nobody else could do and so
yeah yes I'm just to add a wonder were
dickering to me is we have a new world
of you most people don't even know they
have a worldview because you swim in it
but it's a worldview that has all these
elements this new story of creation and
you person then your capabilities and
when you put this worldview together I
would like to say it's the most hopeful
positive guiding worldview that we
possibly could have and I'd like us to
really notice the elements of the
worldview that is coming together for
the three of us and all the sources that
the three of us come from yeah to bring
together the idea that it's not just my
teaching your teaching in other teaching
but it's a worldview that can involve
the world it's an emergent world it
really is and it's delightful and you
know and the reason we keep coming back
to first-person it's how we're all
embodying the teaching it's busy this is
exactly that place in history where
there can't be a split or we actually
have to embody it it has to become us
and we have to become it or there's no
teaching that's right so let's let's
dive in to two pieces you know which are
I think really important pieces we could
highlight and talk about together of
this emergent worldview so in the world
there's this big split that everyone
makes all the time between autonomy
independence in communion being part of
being independent being part of right
are kind of this huge conflict and you
could trace of course all of world
thought and our entire psychology has an
individual human being but the human
being and humanity but the balance
between those two the split between
those two and you can actually trace all
of history who said that one is
essential and reinterpret or the other
you said the other is essential and
reinterpret or the other so for example
the social contract basically says the
basic unit of reality is the individual
to the extent that there's communities
because there's a social contract the
individual gives up some rights to
create some sense of community you have
a kind of you know Marxist tradition
emerging out of Hegel that says the real
reality is the community right and and
the individual only exists to the extent
that they serve the community both
actually deny the other and then
have people to try and make it a kind of
a dialectic there's a kind of dialect
hold dance between autonomy and
communion we're suggesting something
actually beyond all three of those
naturally emerge from our conversation
because actually the psychoactive
quality the intellectual cognitive
quality and the existential emotional
feeling quality of unique self is that
unique self is the place since which you
were pointing to Daniel it's the place
in which autonomy in communion actually
that that antinomy that split disappears
because actually when you wake up in
outrageous love as an outrageous lover
which means that you're in your unique
self your unique incarnation of love
intelligence you're fully yourself
you're radically wildly autonomous and
you're fully part of the larger whole in
the entire split between autonomy and
commune
disappears at a higher level of
consciousness and it's one of the most
important breakthroughs in consciousness
and in order to respond to this new
moment in history which either
dissolution or evolution but it's only
the overcoming of this historical split
possible it is one two and three that I
outlined moving beyond that that can
actually birth a new consciousness and
without that there's no possibility so I
really just want to highlight that
because it's the only place that happens
last sentence and pass it to both of you
you know one of the places people
experience it but they only experience
it in passing is that people have kind
of had like a lot of alcohol or perhaps
another kind of substance I don't know
what it would be but you know maybe
there's other substances that people use
occasionally right but but if someone's
had kind of being a baby aspirin or
something like that right so so and a
person feels like really expanded they
also feel very loving right but actually
that experience right I've expanded and
loving meaning connected and wildly
present is actually fully available when
you're actually having a mad love affair
with reality as an artist lover and the
reason is because actually all of
reality is an expression of outrageous
love so when you awaken as an outrageous
lover your uniqueness is highlighted and
then you're just connected and so that's
a core structural movement in our
symphony well it mean just just build on
that the Incarnation
of the process of creation as Who I am
uniquely and who you are uniquely it
seems to me there's no dualism right at
all right in there and since you are an
expression of that he's an expression of
that and the world as a whole we're all
members of one body right another way of
looking at if you look at Earth from
space
we're obviously members of one body
about to connect and I want to reinforce
that because Daniels what you're saying
particularly about the design of
civilization and self-governance that
would be required it seems to me it's
going to require a connectivity among
these future humans that's right that's
why it's so critical all right yet fully
half that's right that I just like you
to say something about what you think
that would mean for us if we could have
that such an important point I'll say
something to Marx and then that so many
of the problems that we experienced
personally and collectively come from
believing in false dichotomies and so we
optimize one thing at the expense of
another when both are important because
we believe that we have to do that and
the answer is optimized for both of
those things for agency and communion
for freedom and connection for we've all
had the experience of feeling like we
wanted more connection and intimate
relationship and they got so connected
our freedom felt lost or feeling like
our you know we got enough freedom and
the connection was lost and happiness
actually doesn't come from either of the
the poles of sacrifice right so actually
in the later in this course I'm gonna
dive really deep into this whole process
of reconciling paradox and specifically
transcending false dichotomies but do we
want what is good for this organ or this
organ or you know these cells or the all
all of them are the questions actually
don't make any sense when you already
have a higher picture that shows that
they're interconnected right and they
have unique functions to serve and it's
the whole needed by the whole and needs
the whole when you get both what's good
for the individual in the whole is the
same thing so then all the way up the
whole our key
and at every level you're optimizing for
all of them simultaneously and so that
requires optimizing for that for the
units and the relationship and as you're
mentioning so we need to become future
humans but then to make the future
humanity think all of the cells just as
goo aren't interesting right it's the
cells coming together in a very specific
way so how do we bring humans that have
woke up to their unique self that are
Omni considerate that are
comprehensively educated in their unique
ways how do we bring them together in
real synergy that creates humanity as an
emergent yeah thing that's real not just
a bunch of parts bumping and not really
in deep relationship and that requires
it's not arbitrary how they come
together right you can't just hook the
liver up to the small intestine or to
the leg or to the it has to come
together in a very specific way and so
the matching processes the being able to
match needs and resources match
individual skills and genius with the
other places match opportunities for
contribution with need the ability to
identify all of those things properly
match them and having that be having a
cybernetic process that helps facilitate
that a symbiotic intelligence of a you
know human and computer facilitated
cloud facilitated capacity is a big part
of where we're going close to the
technology to do it
one interesting observation from the
cellular life is the membrane of the
multi cell holds and frames the
intelligence that holds and activates
the script of the DNA itself you have to
have a membrane so I've often thought
that the nervous system or the global
brain when it gets turned on
sufficiently could be considered a
membrane of consciousness that when we
have the membrane all the particles that
are in it yeah will be almost naturally
more coherent right intuition yeah yeah
fun way to think about that is we're
talking in number three about the Dunbar
Dunbar number and transcending it that
it's both a limit of empathy and
understanding well we can extend our
empathy by practice but but there is a
limit
and what Dunbar saw was it was the size
of the cortex how many complexities it
could handle and being able to factor
all of the complexities that our
technology has on the world we are one
brain can't do that right and a few
brains talking to each other can do that
but but an intelligent cloud actually
can so it's what is a neocortex large
enough to hold all of it that has a
Dunbar number for all of humanity that
then we can interact with and load
information into and come out of exactly
and we actually can do that now right
now we're really so let's let's kind of
let's wrap this piece of it and go to
another piece you have time so what just
what's the structural piece we have so
you can access it there kind of directly
now right it's the image of transcending
autonomy and communion and you find it
by finding an experience in your life
where you felt totally expanded and at
the same time totally connected right
that's a pointing out instruction for
this new structure of consciousness and
again you know as I pointed out and as
Barbara right deepened into as Daniel
elaborated on all right this is a new
moment right if you look at all entire
history of thought and actually didn't
exist autonomy in commune were always
thought right to at best being a
dialectical dance of two opposites when
actually at a higher level literally the
duality of the dichotomy disappears so
let's jump into it kind of another piece
because you know we were talking offline
Barbara remember yesterday about Tantra
and Technology right and let's kind of
come back to this notion what is Tantra
you know Tantra is this principle of Tom
you know me you know expansion in
Sanskrit so Tantra is this you know it's
a particular word in Sanskrit it exists
in Vedic philosophy but really it's a
it's a it's a moment in consciousness
that actually exists in every tradition
and Tantra is in some sense has two
pieces to it
the first piece it's the principle of
non rejection Tantra means non rejection
nothing is rejected and everything has a
place right and Tantra is a trickster
right it's always it's always upside
down all right it's Tantra is
mischievious right and so that notion
that we actually have to with all of
ourselves embrace all of life that's the
core top
principal and in some sense right we're
actually articulating the new Tantra
right and then the new Tantra is the new
vision right of what's possible ritual
pyres that nothing is left out
everything has a place in the circle and
that's a very powerful just kind of
offer that up and to kind of highlight
that because that's one of the
principles is an emergent new yeah it's
actually been powerful for me just as
we've been going through this process
witnessing something I didn't know would
be as deep a part of it going in even as
we created it is this embracing rejected
elements and synthesizing them and in
almost every one of the sessions so far
there's been a real key theme of
elements right the human experience that
had been rejected for good reasons
because they were shadow versions or
unintegrated versions but the integrated
versions are totally critical to the
full human experience right in paradox
see the liberal world is actually very
non-contract because the liberal world
its shadow is it's a big rejecter yeah
anyone that doesn't agree with its
political correctness yes right so just
like you know we kind of weekly work
we're kind of used to casting the
fundamentalist says right they create
other but we're actually inclusive but
actually the liberal world excludes
fundamentalists and as much as
fundamentalistic slew the liberal world
and actually in the transcendent include
move actually everyone's got a place
around the table at a higher level of
consciousness this is right and you know
what when nature is in a chaos window
like this it seeks structure of a higher
order or it will go to a lower order
it's not just good ideas actually so
when we get into tomorrow it's about the
structure of a co-creative Society what
kind of self-governance would a society
have that would be able to do this I
think that creates kind of a structural
strange attractor right because without
some structure the system can't jump so
it's totally I think that's why we have
so many reactionary but politics
reactionary religions because it's
trying to go somewhere where there was a
structure and the liberal community
doesn't have the structure and we are
just building it right so
a very important contribution right what
we're doing right now totally mm-hmm
don't you have a last thought before I
wrap it here what do you got for us
awesome so let's just maybe put the last
kind of thought in to kind of wrap this
piece and we're really finishing and if
you know where you are now kind of look
at yourself you're finishing the second
third of the course we're about to go
into week 7 8 & 9 and so let's throw one
more dance into the play certainty and
uncertainty and it's Barbra it's really
what you were just talking to and the
classical world we understand the
conservative or the kind of
fundamentalist world
they've got certainties and the liberal
world has uncertainty things right and
each one excludes the other right and as
the fundamentalist word excludes all the
uncertainties right of the liberal world
and the liberal world excludes all of
the certainties of the fundamentalist
world but that's actually a wrong
relationship between certainty and
uncertainty what if we embrace a new
vision which is a critical part of our
emergent new evolutionary worldview
which is part of the interior experience
of becoming a new human which is one we
embrace uncertainty as a spiritual value
we embrace uncertainly as an existential
value and actually dancing in the
uncertainty is actually one of the
expressions of our numinous
and not an uncertainty that's uncertain
because we're lacking information to
resolve it but an uncertainty which is
core Heisenberg's uncertainty right to
the very nature of reality itself so
that's one and then embracing certainty
instead of it is true I am true a core
certainty of being and right the liberal
community has to actually embrace its
certainties right so in others the
dogmatic communities might need to
embrace their uncertainties and the
liberal can meet to embrace its
certainties and in order to actually
articulate right a grand narrative that
can actually be an emergent world order
so we're actually this is not kind of a
liberal response to fundamentalism in
this course this is post liberal and
post fundamentalist well that's emergent
it's emergent by nature by nature which
takes the best of both and integrates it
in a higher place no point I'll just
click on that and then get into
paradoxes a lot of there now we got a
whole dialogue coming off the power
concil but Barbara shared something in
her meditation earlier in the course it
was such a brilliant example of that
where she said feel the evolutionary
spiral that is coming to the core of
your being that is the evolving force
that which is not the force of sameness
but the same force of change and she
said find security in that it's a very
deep thing and there's a be easy to miss
but not find security and what's not
changing but find security in the
patterns of change you know what what is
changing and that you are an expression
of that and that you can navigate that
that you can surf that that was a really
deep thing where certainty isn't
necessary for security and yes yes yes
yes you know and as the implications of
what you're saying but barber said and
of this offering that I just suggested
is that there's another place that we
transcend the old duality yep but
actually it's the certainty of
uncertainty right that actually the
certain thing is it's gonna be different
tomorrow right it's exalt and you can
actually rest in that paradoxically but
I want to say one worry about that the
way I rest in it it's going in a
direction that I like oh my god because
the tendency is towards greater
consciousness right greater freedom and
more complex order that happens to be my
innate desire personally right so right
if you're a future human that probably
is your innate desire for more
consciousness more love more creativity
more freedom so those are intrinsic
values of the emerging properties yeah I
think we really gorgeous hold on to that
it's gorgeous that's gorgeous friends
here's the assignment write down your
five certainties they're yours what are
your five core certainties that are not
explicator that you live your life by
and write down your five uncertainties
and rejoice in them thank you